马普尔小姐探案
制作 Lyra
1932年,烟囱大厦,晚宴
不,不,不,别去,别去
No, no, no. Please, please.
不,不.您不能往那边去,求您
No, no. You mustn't go in there, please, sir.
求您听我的
Now, listen to what I'm saying.
求您听我的,求您别过去
Please listen to me. No, please, please.
名苑猎凶
伦敦 蓓尔美尔街俱乐部 23年后
凯特勒姆,老伙计,我不该问
Caterham, my dear chap, I wouldn't ask,
只不过此事关系重大
only it's a matter of considerable national importance.
总是事关重大不是吗?
Isn't it always?
维也纳那边有了很大进展
We've had the most tremendous approach from Vienna.
继续说
Go on.
奥地利现在成了中立国
Now the Austrians are a nice neutral bunch,
他们很急切地想跟我们英国成为朋友
they're very keen to be friends with us Brits.
什么条件?
What's the offer?
铁矿石
Iron ore.
我们去帮助他们的重工业重整旗鼓
We go in, help them put their heavy industry back on its feet,
可以要多少铁矿拿多少
take home all the iron ore we need.
首相简直不敢相信会有这么好的买卖
The PM can scarcely believe his luck.
不管怎样,维也纳方面要派来一位公使
Anyway, Vienna's sending over an envoy.
路德维格伯爵
Count Ludwig.
我分到的任务是为伯爵安排住处,并且开始起草合约
I've been tasked with sitting the Count down, putting pen to paper
然后设法让他签字
and getting him to sign the contract.
得找个红花绿草,心旷神怡,最重要的是能谈事的地方
Somewhere green and pleasant and, above all, discreet.
你想让他住烟囱大厦?
And you thought of Chimneys?
嗯,你懂的,周末开个室内宴会
Well, you know, a weekend house party.
好酒好菜
Good food, decent cellar.
像以前那样,诶?你说怎么样?行吗?
Just like the old days, eh? What do you say? Do the ayes have it?
实际上,我下个月还想出去度假呢
Well, actually, I was thinking of going on holiday next month.
别瞎扯了,谁9月份出去度假啊
Oh, nonsense. Nobody goes on holiday in September.
再说,咱俩谁跟谁啊
Besides, we're practically family you and I.
只等着你家女儿想通了
Once we bring that girl of yours to her senses.
我们家不如从前啦,房子有点失修
We're not as we were. The house is in some disrepair.
很好啊,有点沧桑感,增加几分情趣
Perfect. Faded grandeur. Adds to the flavour.
这事不能张扬出去
It'll need to be low-key.
那是自然的,只叫好朋友来,此事要谨慎处理
Indeed so. Intimate. Discreet.
选一两个"合适"的客人
One or two guests, sensitively chosen.
当然了,这些个欧洲人都是些势利眼
Of course, these continentals are such fearful snobs.
我会叫我最得力的手下去帮忙的
I'll send my best chap round to help with the setting up.
比尔埃弗斯利,听候差遣
Bill Eversleigh. Yours to serve.
你好
How do you do?
为什么选择烟囱大厦?我们都很多年没举办宴会了
But why Chimneys? It's years since we gave a party.
几十年了,32年以后就没举办过
Decades. Not since '32.
给他看看那封信
Show him the letter.
哪封?   路德维格伯爵写的
The...?   From Count Ludwig.
你看
Here we are.
第四段
Fourth para.
从中间开始读
Halfway down.
我久仰烟囱大厦的大名,听说是英国老建筑里
I have heard that Chimneys is the most prized house...
最负盛名的
..in old England,
如果能瞻仰这座美丽的宫殿
and would count it a singular honour
将是鄙人的无上荣幸
to see that jewelled palace for myself.
这将成为我最想要珍藏的记忆
It is a memory I am most eager to cherish.
要是我吓着你了很抱歉
Sorry to drop in unannounced.
你要是合作我也会温柔一些
If you're gentle with me then I'll be gentle with you.
啊!
Agh!
救命!
Help!
永远,不要...
Never, ever...
碰我妈妈的自行车
..touch mother's bicycle again.
你没事吧?能站起来吗?
Are you all right? Can you stand?
哦,是的,我...   这是最主要的
Oh, yes, I...   Well, that's the main thing.
只要能站起来,一切就...
Once you're up on your pins, then life seems so...
皆有可能
Full of possibility.
没错
Indeed.
我倒不是只在乎我妈的自行车,你知道
Not that I was purely concerned about
poor mother's bicycle, you understand.
我希望不是
Well, I should hope not.
我想那家伙应该吸取教训了,你说呢?
I think the chap got the message, don't you?
他就这么铁马王子一般地冲出来救了我
And there he was, galloping in to save me on his iron horse.
真是世界上最二的骑士了
I mean it really was the most idiotically chivalrous...
怎么了?
What?
弗吉尼亚
Virginia.
你和你亲爱的妈妈一样是无可救药的浪漫主义者
You are as absurdly romantic as your dear mother.
哦,太没有呢
Oh, no. No, no, no.
你这话可说的不对.你要是真的觉得...
Woof woof. Wrong tree. If you honestly...
他是最不合适的人了
He couldn't be more unsuitable.
没钱没钱途
No cash, no prospects.
哦,如果是这样的话...   是啊,就是这样了
Oh, well, then.   Yes, quite. Case closed.
再者说了,他这周对我很冷淡
And, anyway, he's been quite standoffish with me this past week.
大概是觉得无聊了,你说呢?
I expect he's bored of me. Don't you?
哦,必须的.他叫什么?
Oh, yes. Does he have a name?
安东尼凯德"阁下".不过是打引号的
Sir Anthony Cade. Only without the knighthood.
哦,天啊,我还想呢
Oh, dear. I was just thinking.
你那位可怜的国会议员
Your poor MP.
乔治洛马克斯可一刻不耽误
George Lomax won't be the least bit put off.
恰恰相反
On the contrary.
又给你下最后通牒了?
Not another ultimatum?
我要在周日晚上前答应做他太太
I have until Sunday night to consent to be Mrs George Lomax.
要不然呢?   他大概就要入侵波兰了
Or what?   He invades Poland, I suppose.
不管怎么说,他开的条件还是很好的
Anyway, the terms are most generous.
他会安排爸爸在镇上的豪宅住下
He'll put daddy up in a mansion flat in town,
这正合他心意,自从妈妈死了之后他一直想这样
which is all he wants since Mama passed away.
他还会出钱维持烟囱大厦
And he'll even pay to stop Chimneys from falling apart,
我想这对家族很好
which I suppose is jolly good for the family.
前提是你嫁给他
If you marry him.
显然大家期望我会心怀感激
I should be more grateful, obviously.
我想感激大概不是一段幸福婚姻的基石
Well, I'm not sure gratitude is the basis for a happy marriage.
不过话说回来,这方面我没什么发言资格
Well, no, no. Not that I am any sort of expert.
哪的话,妈妈一直说你是她所有亲戚里最理智的了
No, no, no, no, Mummy always said
you were the most eminently sensible of all her cousins.
她的婚姻是非常成功的
Well, she certainly made a splendid marriage.
要说幸福啊,本该很简单的不是吗?
It should be so simple, shouldn't it, being happy?
应该是一见倾心的,不是吗
I mean, one ought to see it, and just know.
现在你来了,我们要放纵一下
Well, now that I've got you here
we are going to have a riot, you and I.
这是我待字闺中的最后一个周末了
My last weekend as an eligible spinster.
你玩游戏吗?   我尽量吧
Are you game?   Well, I'll do my best.
好了!
Well!
我来这里住你父亲没意见吗?
Are you quite sure it's all right with your father, having me along?
爸爸很高兴呢
Oh, Daddy's thrilled.
再说我也去圣玛丽米德做过客
And, anyway, you've had me down to St Mary Mead.
礼尚往来嘛
It's only fair I return the favour.
来,看.17页
Here, look. Page 17.
是不是个帅锅?
Isn't he a dish?
安东尼凯德
Anthony Cade.
一时兴起罢了
Some passing whim.
弗吉尼亚很纯真,很容易受触动.这也是她的魅力
Virginia is innocent, easily led. It's all part of her charm.
也许她只是玩玩罢了
Perhaps she's off for a bit of fun, sir.
我的好伙伴
My short trousers chum,
我们总得学会放下这些幼稚的东西
We must all learn to put away, childish things.
她不是把凯德也叫来了吧
I say she's not bringing Cade along, is she?
没有,先生.她带了一位马普尔小姐来
No, sir. She's coming with a Miss Marple.
我们认识这人吗?
Do we know her?
我想不认识
Not that I'm aware of.
我以为你核对过客人的名单了
I thought you were cross the guest list.
我核对过了,当然核对过了
Oh, I am, absolutely.
马普尔小姐,一听就是没见过世面的小姑娘
Marple, some fresh hatch little...
跟你很搭呢
Something for you obviously.
至于弗吉尼亚,我希望你对她没什么念头
Regarding Virginia, I trust you have no ambition of your own.
哪会呀   因为你是没希望的
What's a question?   Because that wouldn't do at all.
我不想你受伤而已
One wouldn't want you to be hurt.
受伤的机会都没有,先生
No chance of that, sir.
什么事,柴德维尔?
Yes, Treadwell?
你的客人到了,先生
Your guest has arrived, sir.
这么快?
Already?
肩往后,关键时刻到了,学着点
Shoulders back. Cometh the hour. Watch and learn.
爵爷桌上的信
Letters for posting on his Lordship's table.
请您用快递寄出去
Send them express, if you'd be so kind.
路德维格伯爵,您好!
Count Ludwig!
瞧瞧
Oh, look.
他要亲上人家的屁股了
He's practically licking his shoes.
伯爵要以为这是英国的奇风异俗了
The Count might think it's some sort of quaint British custom.
您的到来是我国的荣幸
有点早了,这样更好
A little early, but so much the better.
恰恰相反,我来的太晚了
是啊,这房子很美
Indeed, a lovely house, yes.
他像是上个世纪的人似的
He seems like he's from another age.
你说他能不能说英语啊
I wonder if he speaks any English.
签张支票需要会几句英语呀?
How much English do you need to sign a cheque?
我...金属...你...钞票大大地
Me metal. You big, big dollars.
玛德琳?
Madeleine?
爸爸,别傻了,我是弗吉尼亚啊
Don't embarress yourself, papa, it's Virginia.
是弗吉尼亚啊,我来看看你
Virginia. Pops in a visit.
是啊,我没听到你进来
Yes, I didn't hear you come in.
爸爸您好!
Hello Daddy!
真抱歉,亲爱的
So sorry, darling.
啊,亲爱的简
Ah, dear Jane.
克莱门特
Clement.
都有...多少年...   是啊,自从葬礼就没见了   是啊
It's been... Well...   Yes, not since the funeral.   Yes.
玛德琳死后你一直对我女儿这么好   惭愧
You've been so kind to my daughter since we lost Madeleine.   No.
你的花园怎么样了
How's your garden?
不怎么繁茂啊
Hardly thriving, I'm afraid.
爸爸,你也整理一下自己的仪容啊
Daddy, you might have made a bit of an effort.
不用管我,我现在就是个怪老头了
Oh, pay no attention to me. I'm just the odd-job man these days.
哦,看啊,这不是那位国家遗产局的那个女人吗
Oh, look. I see you've invited that nice lady from National Heritage.
希尔达贝金索普?
Hilda Blenkinsopp?
不,不. 哦,不!
No. No. Oh, no!
班铎,别生气,她很想来这里
Now, Bundle, don't get cross. She was very keen to be invited...
我们说好不让她再来了
She's banned. We agreed.
对,但是国家遗产局出价很合适
Yes, but the National Heritage have made a very sensible offer.
烟囱大厦已经在这个家族传了几代人了,它就是这个家的一部分
Chimneys has been in the family for centuries. It is family.
没错亲爱的,但是我们已经负担不起了,这你知道的
Yes, but, darling, you know we can't afford to keep the place on.
我们会想办法的,我们总是能想到办法
We will manage. We always do.
她心情不错啊
Well, she's on good form.
国家遗产局已经接手郡里13座老宅子了
National Heritage has taken on 13 homes and gardens in the county.
为贵族而建,为人民而维系
Built for the few, fit for the many,
我就是冲着这样的前景努力的   谢谢
that's the England I'm fighting for.   Thank you.
巫婆的计谋得逞了
The witch found who she want.
不管怎么说,你都想不到人们是怎么涌入这些个老房子的
Still, you'd be amazed how these old places fill up.
有钱人的旧宅,谁不想看看啊
Homes of the former great, draw such a crowd.
特别是到了周末
Especially at the weekends.
等我们把那块土地清理好
Once we get that patch sorted out.
那块土地!这些花园是国王设计的
That patch! These gardens were designed by King.
是嘛,谁都有闲得没事的时候啊
Oh, well, dear, I suppose we all have our off days.
上流社会啊,埃弗斯利.我说什么来着!
High society, Eversleigh. What did I say?
提升环境的品味,先生
Embellish the scene, sir.
提升环境的品味,科学家,工业巨头...
Embellish the scene. Scientists. Captains of industry...
你都带了谁?拖把头和水桶腰
What do you bring me? Mrs Mop and Mrs Bucket.
特勒姆说灌点杜松子酒
Caterham says they're both first class
两位就都是上流社会的人了
if you get a bit of gin down them.
哦,是嘛?   有问题吗?
Oh, does he?   Problem?
完全没有,先生
Not at all, sir.
您的客人很...多元化
Very diverse guest list.
很好,那我要去跟她们聊聊了
Good. Well, I should join in.
你特意安排的吗?
Was this your doing?
乔治要接受我们真实的样子
George will have to take us as he finds us.
怎么了?   嫁给我吧
What?   Marry me.
比尔
Bill.
女人空腹的时候可别求婚
Never propose on an empty stomach.
晚饭之后再问我吧
Ask me again after supper.
你没事情要做吗?
Don't you have to be somewhere?
挺热的是不是?
Sultry, isn't it?
你做头发了吗?
What have you done to your hair?
没有
Not a thing.
你能注意到真好啊,亲爱的
Sweet of you to notice, darling.
你没忘记你答应会在周日晚上前回复我吧?
You haven't forgotten that you promised me an answer by Sunday night?
就快要到了
The clock is ticking.
请原谅,但是你们看起来太美了
Forgive me, but you all looked so perfect.
像是画里出来的人
Like you had stepped out of a photograph.
路德维格伯爵,请允许我介绍,克莱门特瑞佛
Count Ludwig, allow me to introduce Clement Revel,
凯特勒姆家族的第九代
Ninth Marquis of Caterham.
您好   很高兴认识您
How do you do?   The honour is entirely mine.
晚上好,夫人们
Good evening, madam.
这两位就是您女儿吗?
And these are your two little Revels?
能赏脸吗?
Would you indulge a fading guest?
赏个光嘛
Why not?
我真的不会跳舞.您邀请她跳吧
I've two left feet. So why don't you try her?
反正大家都喜欢她
Because everyone else seems to.
节奏感多好啊
Oh, for a sense of rhythm.
舞姿真优雅
Such a graceful dancer.
他们都跳的不错不是吗?
Well, they all are, aren't they?
不过这可算不上是什么有实用的修养
Still, hardly the most practical accomplishment.
您第一次来英国吗?
Is this your first visit to our shores?
不,我都来过好几次了
No, I am an inveterate itinerant, I'm afraid.
至少年轻的时候常来
Or I was, once upon a time.
您在笑话我呢
Now you are laughing at me.
没有,没有,只是您的英语
No, no, no, it's just your English.
说得真好
Splendid.
我的老师很严格的
I had a highly disciplined teacher, you see.
她只教我说绕口令
She taught me only tongue-twisters.
吃葡萄不吐葡萄皮
Inveterate itinerant.
Inveterate itinerant!
晚饭要凉了
Your dinner is getting cold.
很好,非常好
Very good. Excellent.
班铎,你带大家进去啊?   好啊
Bundle, will you lead on?   Yes, of course.
贝金索普小姐,您先请
Miss Blenkinsopp, after you.
请跟我来,小姐们
Follow me, ladies.
您能来真好
Very good, you're with us.
您来吗?   哦
Shall we?   Oh.
晚餐很不错,谢谢
A splendid dinner, thank you.
是的,很丰盛
Yes, very filling.
请允许我问一下
Forgive my asking, sir.
您想来我家是因为这建筑吗?
Your interest in my house, is it for architecture?
不,不,我对建筑并不懂
No, no. I have no head for grand design, for architecture.
你家的画...   好的大都卖掉了
Your paintings...   We sold most of the decent ones.
我们还留着这副凡代克的画
We still have our Van Dyck.
是啊
So I see.
这位是什么人啊?   一位什么公爵的
Who is this fellow?   Some old duke.
里士满的呢
Richmond. Duke of.
里士满,是啊
Richmond. Yes.
要是既不为了艺术品,也不为了建筑,那是...?
So if it's not the art, or the architecture, then...?
历史啊
Oh, the history.
据说这房子接待过不少伟大的人
The great men rumoured to have met within these walls.
签订条约,探讨政务
Treaties, affairs of state,
甚至战争也在这里的咖啡和雪茄间开始和结束
wars, even, begun and ended here over coffee and cigars.
哪有这么玄乎呀
Oh, nothing so biblical, I assure you.
凯特勒姆这是在谦虚呢
He's being modest, aren't you, Caterham?
烟囱大厦名声在外
Chimneys had quite a reputation.
那现在怎么沦落了?
So what happened?
你说什么?
What was that?
出了点事
We ran into some bother.
你是说1932年的那次宴会?
Oh, the party of 1932?
哦,老黄历了
Oh, that old yarn.
我们刚从加拉加斯(委内瑞拉首都)回国来
Well, we'd come back from an embassy posting. Caracas.
结果那也是我最后一次做驻外大使了
It was my last one, as it turned out.
那年弗吉尼亚还没出生呢
It was before Virginia was born.
不管怎样,那晚真是不错
Anyway, it was quite a night.
你妈妈很会举办宴会的,花园里还有请来的乐队在演奏
Your mother always gave wonderful parties,
with a band out in the garden.
我听说过
I remember the story, yes.
你当时还在场呢,是不是乔治?
You were there yourself, weren't you, George?
去帮把手.我陪着索梅塞夫人去的
Helping out. I was accompanying Lady Somerset.
我很受...启发
It was um...most instructive.
这张照片就是那时拍的吗?
Is this it here?
是的.   这是在哪?
Yes.   Where is that?
玫瑰园   啊
The rose garden.   Ah.
我们动人的维也纳华尔兹
Our lovely Viennese waltz.
您的歌声真好听   谢谢
Charming singing voice.   Thank you.
不过,那晚还出了点事
Anyway, there was a bit of a to-do
索梅塞公爵夫人当晚借来了一个很大的胸针戴着...
because the Duchess of Somerset
had borrowed a large brooch for the evening. On her...
大胸针?
Large brooch?
爸爸,那是印度迈索尔的钻石
Daddy, it was the Mysore Diamond from India,
大概是世界上最有名的钻石了
possibly the most revered diamond in the world.
嗯,不管是啥,早餐的时候发现它不见了
Well, whatever it was, by breakfast time it had disappeared.
被偷了,被个一无是处的客厅女仆,叫艾格尼丝的偷走了
Stolen. By some good-for-nothing parlour maid named Agnes.
客厅女仆,像小说里的故事呢!
A parlour maid. What an English saga!
那个女仆当晚就失踪了,不是吗?
The maid vanished overnight. Isn't that right?
钻石也再没找到
And the diamond was never ever to be found again.
还要咖啡吗?   哦,是的,谢谢
Anyone for more coffee?   Oh, yes, please.
这个艾格尼丝是个什么样的女孩子?
So what sort of girl was she, this Agnes?
也许没人注意过她?
Or did nobody notice?
只有19岁,我想肯定是一时冲昏了头脑
Well, only 19 years old. She must have lost her head, I suppose.
不管怎样,这件事让我的外交生涯结束了
Anyway, it meant the end of my career in the diplomatic service.
说起来真是丢人
All rather shameful.
女士们能不能让我们单独...
Well, if the ladies can spare us...?
谈生意   是,当然
To business.   Indeed. Yes.
我给你们生意
I give you business.
你要我们的铁矿啊,洛马克斯议员?
You want our iron, Mr Lomax, MP?
那是当然的   我只提出一个要求
Well, naturally.   I make one request.
烟囱大厦
Chimneys.
把烟囱大厦作为给我个人的礼物
Give me Chimneys as a personal favour. And, in return, I guarantee
作为回报,我会保证,你们能要多少拿多少
you can take home all the riches your heart desires.
这我不知道...   我们不卖房子
Well, I'm not sure...   We are not for sale.
不卖,你说啊
Not for sale. Tell them.
你们去打打桥牌怎么样?
Why don't you all try a hand of bridge?
哦,真见鬼   好的
Oh, for God's sake.   Yes.
你确定了吗?    是的
You're quite sure?    Absolutely.
那好,在这里...签字
Very well. Then mark your cross... ..here.
伯爵,现在请在这里签字
Now, Count, if you'd be kind enough to sign here.
好的
With great pleasure.
洛马克斯先生!先生!
Mr Lomax! Sir!
简!   发生什么事了?   我不知道
Jane!   What's happening?   I don't know.
几点了?
What time is it?
请你们到楼下去
If you'd all like to gather downstairs...
对不起,把你们都吵醒了
I'm sorry to have to wake you all up
但是洛马克斯先生的一位警卫被打昏了
but one of Mr Lomax's security staff was found unconscious.
是不是?
Is that so?
是的,先生.是罗伯茨
That's right, sir. Roberts.
埃弗斯利,我们都在这里了吗?   是的
All present and correct, Eversleigh?   Indeed so.
我想还少一位呢
I believe we're one short.
伯爵   除了伯爵
The Count.   Out for the count.
我倒不奇怪,想想他喝成什么样了
That's no surprise, considering how he was knocking it back.
看看能不能叫醒他
See if you can raise him.
他不在屋里,先生
He's not in his room, sir.
什么?   他在哪?
What?   Where is he?
我想我们应该搜一搜
Perhaps we need a search party.
没错,杰夫斯,你和罗伯茨把后门封锁上
Indeed. Jaffers you and Roberts seal off the back door.
班铎,你去看看以前仆人的住处
Bundle, the old servants' quarters.
埃弗斯利,你和贝金索普小姐在一楼找
Eversleigh You and Miss Blenkinsopp, the ground floor,
我和弗吉尼亚在楼上找
and Virginia and I will look upstairs.
弗吉尼亚怎么不能和我一起找?
Why Can't Virginia come with me?
没时间了
We don't have time for this.
你干嘛总想坏我的事?
Why do you always undermine me?
你们俩消停一会行不?
Will you two kindly desist?
谢谢了
Thank you.
弗吉尼亚,你能不能上楼把他的药拿下来?
Now, Virginia, can you run upstairs and collect his medicine?
简在这里看着他   好的
Jane will remain here and keep an eye on him.   Of course.
其他人我们分头找.好吗?
The rest of us can just as well look by ourselves. Agreed?
路德维格伯爵
Count Ludwig.
这样不好吧
I wouldn't think that's wise.
大概不好
Probably not.
你来点?
What about you?
好啊
Why not.
我们都多久没说过话了啊,你和我?
Seems ages since we talked, you and I?
玛德琳这些年来也没怎么跟你联络了
Had been Madeleine rather lost touch with you over the years.
不在一起难免会渐渐疏远吧
One grows apart, I think.
大概是的
I suppose.
不过,我真的很感激你一直为我留心弗吉尼亚的事
Still, I'm so grateful that you keep an eye on Virginia for me.
当爸爸的也有做不到的事啊
A father can only do so much.
这几年来,自从玛德琳...
And these past years, since Madeleine...
反正过的不容易啊
Well, it's not been easy.
我听说你想搬去伦敦住
I gather you're hoping to move to London.
班铎可不允许
Not if Bundle can help it.
哦,可怜的孩子,这里是她唯一的家
Oh, poor child, it's the only home she's ever known, you see
但实际上记忆根本不是什么安慰
The truth is memories are no consolation.
那些好的也不是
Not even the good ones.
我把你的药拿来了
I've brought your medicine.
谢天谢地我还有一双女儿啊
Thank God for my darling girls.
爸爸
Daddy.
乔治?   等会的!
George?   Not now!
那声音好像是...   是开枪吗?
That sounded almost like...   Was that a gunshot?
关上那扇门!
Someone close that door!
你们找到他了吗?
Well, where is he? Any sign?
你听到了吗?   大概半个郡都听到了
Did you hear it?   I think half the county heard it.
他不会凭空消失啊
He can't have just vanished.
没有什么小门,小屋子什么的?
Are there no doorways, no outbuildings?
你想不会是...   我们的秘门
You don't think...?   Our little door.
啊!   拿着
Ah!   Take that.
墙上应该有电筒,在这呢
Should be torches on the wall. Here is it.
自己拿一个   走啊,简
Help yourself.   Come on, Jane.
这是血吗?   看起来像
What is that? Blood?   Looks like it.
安东尼?
Anthony?
我想他是中枪了   什么?
I think he's been shot.   What?
奇...奇...奇...
Want! Want! Want!
路德维格伯爵?能听到我说话吗?
Count Ludwig? Can you hear me?
他还有气吗?   摸摸他的脉搏
Is he breathing?   Check his pulse.
你能听到我吗?
Can you hear me?
哦,天啊
Oh, God.
不是我干的   我摸不到脉搏
It wasn't me.   I can't find a pulse.
我想他是死了
I think he's dead.
不是我干的!
It wasn't me!
弗吉尼亚! 弗吉尼亚! 弗吉尼亚! 弗吉尼亚!
Virginia! Virginia! Virginia! Virginia!
他是个多可爱的人啊
He was such an enchanting man.
还是我们的客人
And he was our guest.
我相信事情不是我们想的那样的
I'm sure there's a perfectly innocent explanation.
弗吉尼亚!
Virginia!
我得去找他   你敢!
I should go to him.   Don't you dare.
别,回来!
Don't, come back.
弗吉尼亚!   安东尼
Virginia!   Anthony.
我的爱人   安东尼!
My love.   Anthony!
你不能进去,小姐   我能跟他说话吗?
You can't go in, miss.   May I at least speak to him?
恐怕不行啊   哦求你了,求你了
I'm sorry, miss.   Oh, please. Please.
安东尼你为什么会出现在这里?
Anthony, what are you even doing here?
弗吉尼亚...你得答应我一件事
Virginia... You must promise me something.
什么事都行
Anything.
求你...答应我你会忘记我
Please...promise me you'll forget me.
安东尼?你吓着我了
Anthony? You're scaring me.
安东尼
Anthony.
芬驰
Finch.
见到你太好了
Thank God. Good to see you again.
芬驰探长,苏格兰场的领袖
Inspector Finch. The guru of Scotland Yard.
芬驰?他长得像只猫,你不觉得吗?
Finch? He looks quite like a cat, don't you think?
我讨厌猫   嘘!
I loathe cats.   Ssh!
我猜他在内政部一定有不少粉丝吧
I gather he has devotees all over the Home Office.
大家都觉得他很神秘呢
They regard him as some sort of mystic.
有点像诺里奇的朱利安,不过是拥有逮捕权的
A bit like Julian of Norwich, only with powers of arrest.
我们对受害人都有什么了解?
What do we know of the victim?
1892年生于维也纳
Born Vienna, 1892.
父母有钱,年轻的时候常到处周游
Wealthy parents. Travelled about a good deal in his youth.
就是喜欢到处玩的那种人
Something of a wandering spirit.
战后很快进入了政界
Entered politics soon after the war.
我让我的人在镇上找个地方给你住
I can get my chap to find you a place in the town.
没必要,我就住在烟囱大厦
No need. I shall be staying at Chimneys.
谋杀犯可不打点上班
Murder rarely keeps office hours.
你好
Hello.
呼吸一下新鲜空气
Bit of fresh air.
如果处理的不好,会成为政治上的灾难
Politically this could be a disaster, if not handled with care.
是啊
Indeed.
就是说女士们都早早休息了?
So the ladies retired early?
我们要谈生意
We had some business.
与此无关   他要买下烟囱大厦
Er...not relevant.   He wanted to buy Chimneys.
他要买下烟囱大厦?
He wanted to buy Chimneys?
他的建议是由政府买下这栋房子,再以礼物的形式赠予伯爵
Well, the proposal was that the government would purchase the house,
and then pass it on to Count Ludwig as a gift.
算是贿赂吗?   别瞎说...
A bribe?   Don't be absurd...
是给他个人的贿赂
A personal bribe.
作为回报,他会把他们的重工业分一杯羹给我们
In return for which, he hands over a share of their heavy industry.
我们对此事的道德立场是什么?
Where do we stand on that, morally?
我想反正是不会拒绝的
Well back, I'd have thought.
有买卖的文件吗?
Is there paperwork for this sale?
签好字,封好印,锁在我屋抽屉里呢
Signed, sealed and in my room on the top drawer.
现在已经没用了
All academic now, of course.
了解
Understood.
凯特勒姆勋爵,一扇门关上了,另一扇打开了
As one door closes, another stands ajar, Lord Caterham.
确实
Indeed.
各位先生们是什么时候休息的?
So you gentlemen retired at...
差一刻十一点的时候
About a quarter to eleven.
直到我们被铃声惊醒
Until we were woken by the fire bell.
洛马克斯先生!先生!
Mr Lomax! Sir!
什么时候?   差二十分到午夜
At what time?   Twenty to midnight.
我们都到了楼下
We all met downstairs.
没见到伯爵,所以我们就去找他
No sign of the Count. So off we went, looking for him.
除了克莱门特和我
All save Clement and myself.
然后就砰地一声
Next thing... Boom!
枪声吗?
The gunshot?
他一直都在通道里,就几码之外
He was in the passageway all along. Just a few yards away.
武器上有指纹吗?
Any fingerprints on the weapon?
没有
Regrettably not.
但是我们抓到了犯人,安东尼凯德
Still, we have the culprit. Anthony Cade.
当然了,要问他几句话
He has one or two questions to answer, certainly.
我能看看尸体吗?   我带你去   谢谢
May I see the body?   I shall take you there at once.   Thank you.
哦,还是让...
Or perhaps Miss...
马普尔   马普尔小姐,方便吗?
Marple.   Marple. Yes. If it's no inconvenience?
哦,行啊,没问题
Oh. Well, no, not at all.
都过了就寝时间近一个小时了,他在这里干嘛?
What was he doing here, almost an hour after he went to bed?
晚餐时他说对凡代克的画很感兴趣
He showed an interest over dinner in the Van Dyck portrait.
或许是回来...   自己欣赏一会?
I suppose the Count could have returned...    A private viewing?
可能是吧
I suppose.
碰巧秘门开了
And chanced upon the secret door.
不过这世上没什么巧合不是吗?
Except that nothing quite happens by chance, does it? Not really.
或者这只是我的偏见?
Or is that my tidy-minded preference?
我注意到你身边没有人
I see you don't have a man with you.
什么?
I'm sorry?
嗯,一般探长都会带个人
Well, inspectors nowadays tend to have a man with them.
啊   或许你喜欢自己独行?
Ah.   Perhaps you prefer to muse alone?
或许没人愿意跟我做搭档   哦
Perhaps no man would have me.   Oh.
这些血...   他就在这里被射伤
This blood...   He was shot here.
也可能是从这边一路爬或者走或者被拖过来的
And crawled, staggered, or was dragged this-a-way...
在这里被发现时倒在凯德先生的怀里
..where he was found in the arms of Mr Cade. Here.
然后在这里倒向可怜的弗吉尼亚
Before falling on poor Virginia. Here.
显然是这样的
All fairly straightforward, apparently.
啊哈
Ah-ha.
是封信吗?
Is it a letter?
不是
Not quite.
高音谱号   还是位艺术鉴赏家呢
A treble clef.    A virtuoso.
您能拿着这个帮我研究研究吗,马普尔小姐
Perhaps you could take this and study it for me, Miss Marple.
好的
Very well.
伯爵死前说了些什么
The Count said something before he died.
奇,奇...   奇?你确定吗?
Want, want...   Want? Are you sure?
嗯   什么意思呢?
Mm-hm.    Meaning?
或许是想说什么话,临死之言
Well, I suppose we all want something, even at death's door.
遗言之类的
Kiss of life, perhaps?
你怎么到这里的?   我从那边翻墙进来
How did you get here?   I climbed over the wall.
我要进房子里
I was eager to get up to the house
这位先生挡住了我的路
and this gentleman was blocking the path.
能站一下位置吗,先生?
Would you mind, sir?
我记得
Well, as I remember,
我从这边过来
I came from around here.
我看到了他,我慌神了
Then I spotted the gentleman, I panicked,
然后...   你袭击了他
and then...   You hit him.
是的,真抱歉
Yes, I am sorry about that.
用这个吗?
Using this?
是的
Exactly.
是什么时间?   11点33分整
What time was that?   11:33. Precisely.
我记得这么清楚是因为我看表了
I remember because I looked at my wrist watch.
你眼力真好啊,凯德先生
I envy your eyesight, Mr Cade.
是这样的
You see, that's the thing.
我看到表是因为楼上有间房间的灯亮了
I know, because there was a light on in one of the upstairs rooms.
二楼,右数第二间
It was first storey and then second to the right.
我记得有人生火了
Now, I can remember because someone had lit a fire.
这么暖和的天还生火吗
Rather a warm night for a fire.
上面的烟囱里有烟冒出来
Well, there was definitely smoke coming out of the chimney above.
反正,这个时候我已经很慌乱了
Anyway, at this stage common sense sounded the retreat.
你听到铃声了吗?
Did you heed the warning?
没有,就像我说的,我慌神了
Well, sadly, common sense and I are no longer on speaking terms
我继续走,进了门
so I carried on along here and through the door.
然后到这里
And then I came down here,
打开活板门
opened the trap door
然后我听到了枪声
and then I heard the gunshot.
啊...   我的天!
Ahh...   Good God!
他已经中枪了?   是的
He'd been shot already?   Yes.
你知道是谁射伤他的吗?   不知道
Any idea who shot him?   Afraid not.
但是左轮手枪只离你三英尺远,受害人就倒在你脚下
And yet, the revolver three feet from you, the victim at your heels?
我根本没看见左轮
I swear I never saw any revolver.
凯德先生,能问问你到底来这干嘛的吗?
Mr Cade, may one ask what you were actually doing here?
我倒是在想你什么时候会问起这个呢
Yes, well, I did wonder when you'd get around to asking that.
事实上
The truth is,
我不想不争取一下就让给洛马克斯
I couldn't let Lomax have his way without putting up a fight.
你指的是弗吉尼亚吗?   是的
His way with Virginia?   Yes.
我想好了静静等着
I thought to myself: just sit tight
早餐的时候突然出现吓你们一跳
and then burst in at breakfast and give you all a fright.
你确实吓着我们了
You certainly did that.
警官在你的口袋里找到了这个
The constable found this in your pocket.
是谁写的?
Oh. Any idea who wrote it?
"亲爱的凯德,来烟囱大厦,花园里有个活板门"
"Dear Cade, come to Chimneys. There's a trapdoor in the garden.
"11点45分整"
11:45 sharp."
什么?这不是我写的
What? I didn't write this.
你确定吗?凯德先生好像觉得是...   这不是我的风格
Are you sure? Mr Cade seems to think...   Not my style.
我不会这么匆忙的写一封情书
A love note is not something you just dash off.
你笑什么
I don't see what you're sniggering at.
对不起,我二了,我能看看吗?
I'm sorry - idiot - may I see?
拿过来
Hand it over.
从邮戳来看是本地寄出的
It appears from the postmark to have been sent locally,
快递,昨天早上寄出的
express service, as late as yesterday morning.
这信不是你们寄出去的吗?
So, none of you sent this letter?
这个假设怎么样?
How's this for a hypothesis?
凯德自己打好信
Cade types the letter himself,
坐车去村里寄了出去
takes the train down to the village and posts it.
就是为了来引诱弗吉尼亚的
All in a cynical bid to ensnare Virginia.
乱说!我昨天早上还和他喝茶来着
Rubbish! I was having tea with him yesterday morning.
在艾治威大道的街角里昂
At the Lyons Corner House on the Edgware Road.
而且我们很愉快
And it was very nice.
洛马克斯先生,你的房间是倒数第二间是吗?
And, Mr Lomax, your room is second from the end, isn't it?
是又怎样?
So?
铃响之前,那里有灯光
There was a light on there last night. Just before the alarm sounded.
胡说!谁说的?
Rubbish! Says who?
哦,凯德
Oh. Cade.
是为了分散你的视线,探长
Blatant attempt to put you off your game, Inspector.
安东尼
Anthony.
我说过了,我不值得你牺牲
I told you. I'm not worth the sacrifice.
我会自己做判断的,谢谢了
I'll be the judge of that, thank you very much.
请你们一直待在烟囱大厦,等待我们的进一步通知
If you would be so good as to
remain at Chimneys until further notice.
那他呢?你就打算让他在这里闲逛吗?
And what about him? You're not going to let him wander about?
我们会盯着他的,我们会盯着你们所有人
No, we'll keep an eye on him. Keep an eye on all of you.
很不正常,不是吗?
It's quite perverse, isn't it?
他是很有乐感的一个人
He was such a musical fellow.
很好的舞者
Quite the dancer.
我总是说曲调的作用是鼓舞士气,不是吗?
I always say the point of a tune is to boost the morale, surely?
确实
Indeed.
有什么要我帮忙的吗?   啊柴德维尔,就找你呢
May I help?   Ah, Treadwell, the very man.
弗吉尼亚那本音乐手册在哪?你知道我说的哪本吗?
Where is that musical handbook of Virginia's? You know the one?
《闪电的节奏》?
Hits Of The Blitz?
就是那本.来吧
The very nelly. Come.
不对...不对...
No...No...
哦
Oh.
正研究着呢,马普尔小姐?
Hard at it, Miss Marple?
探长,嗯...我有点看不明白了
Inspector, it's... I'm a little lost.
几乎看不出音节在哪开始在哪结束
One can hardly see where one bar ends and the next begins.
不好意思
I'm sorry, forgive me.
这...   基本上就不是音乐
It's...   Hardly music at all.
会不会...   我都觉得...
Could it be...   I almost wonder...
不好意思   你说
Forgive me.   Go on.
我在想,是不是
Oh, well, I wonder, is it possible,
这实际上是一封密信
it is, in fact, a message of some sort in code?
你在想什么啊?
What were you thinking of?
你根本不了解这个人,也不了解他的家人
You know nothing about the man or his people.
我知道他很风趣很冲动
I know he's funny and reckless
他妈妈有辆很好的自行车
and his mother has a jolly nice bicycle,
而我觉得这比认识些大人物要强的多
which I happen to think counts for more than
a dozen columns in Who's Who.
他开了个酒吧   哦,多感人啊   在非洲,布拉瓦约
He ran a bar.   Oh, how philanthropic.   In Africa. In Bulawayo.
他有个朋友,生意伙伴
He had a friend with him, they were business partners.
他的朋友叫什么?   吉米麦格拉斯
And does this friend have a name?   Jimmy McGrath.
有一段时间还做的挺好的
They did rather well, for a time,
但是吉米有酗酒的毛病
but Jimmy liked to drink, you see.
把钱都赌光了
He gambled it all away.
一场里全输给一个比勒陀利亚来的人了
Lost it in one sitting to a gentleman from Pretoria.
你认识他还不得两星期
You've known him for less than a fortnight.
爸爸   啊,凯特勒姆
Daddy.   Ah, Caterham.
给你女儿讲讲道理
Knock some sense into your daughter.
哦,能讲清的人得多猛啊
Oh, well it's a brave man who'd dare to.
你妈妈会怎么说呢?
What would your mother have said?
你少用我妈说事,我妈妈总是做她真心喜欢的事情
My mother, you presume to speak about, always went with her heart.
是吗?
Isn't that so?
她也教我这样做
And she raised me to do the same.
弗吉尼亚!   安东尼不是凶手
Virginia!   Anthony is no murderer.
时间不多了   啊!
The clock is ticking.    Ah!
瘦得像猴,滑得像蛇,小...
Slimy, slithering, little, Uhh...
该死的乔治洛马克斯是我最讨厌的人
George bloody Lomax was the last one on earth.
我无意中听到
I'm not meant to know,
他的女仆告诉我,他睡觉还戴发网呢,你能想象吗
his maid told me, he sleep with a hairnet, can you imagine.
别告诉这种事,反而让我觉得他有点可爱
Don't tell me that, always makes me like him a little bit.
我喜欢健康的男人
I love valentina man,
再说每个人都有些小秘密,不是吗?
besides, I mean everybody has a little skeleton, don't they?
一不小心就会暴露出来
Any moment tend to leap out of the closet.
在大家面前出丑
Dance and gigger of the bloody society pages.
怎么了?   没什么,你可以换牌
What?   No, you're allow to swap cards if you like.
我为什么要换呢
Why would I want to,
这是什么牌?
well, what is it?
同花顺
Flush
你别故意输给我就为了让我开心
Don't make me win just to cheer me up.
对不起,管不住自己
Sorry, can't help myself.
有你真好,就像暴风雨里的港湾
Thank God for you sweetie, like a port in the storm.
比那个要多一点吧?
Bit more than that I hope?
我是说你讨厌乔治
I mean with George...
至于那位凯德先生...
And as for your pound Mr. Cade...
别说话
Don't.
对不起,亲爱的,但是总得有人说啊
I'm sorry darling, but it has to be said.
死囚区可不是办婚礼的地方
Death row is no place for a wedding.
不好笑
Not funny.
但是很显然我们都在房子里的时候他在通道里呢
But he quite obviously was in that tunnel
while we were all in the house.
真的是这样吗?
Or were we?
我们真的都在房子里吗?
来啊
Come on.
她在干嘛呢?
What's she doing?
想证明她爱人的清白
Trying to prove her lover innocent.
她打算怎么做到呢?
How does she propose to do that?
我不知道
I have no idea.
不管怎么样,凯德先生都是在通道里被发现的
Like it or not, Mr Cade was still there,
身旁还有尚有余温的抢呢
in the tunnel, with the smoking gun.
你会逮捕他吗?   我很想
Will you arrest him?   I'm tempted.
他很粗心,还说谎
He's careless, all the lies he tells.
信,还有房子亮灯什么的
The letter, that business with the light on in the house...
凯德那样的人狡兔三窟
A man like Cade requires plenty of rope.
我们都是这样,你也是
Like most of us. Even you.
我也是嫌犯吗?
Am I under suspicion?
我知道你的秘密,马普尔小姐
I know your secret, Miss Marple.
你喜欢解谜题
You are a puzzle-outer of mysteries.
我确实参与过一些谜题
I muddle through one or two.
都是碰上了
It's a matter of association.
我...我的村子...   圣玛丽米德村
My... my village, you see...   St. Mary Mead
是,是,是个很不错的社区
Yes, yes, it's a most pleasent community.
有意思的是...全部的生活都在我的窗外走过
Funny how... the whole of life seems to pass by my window.
比你想的要丰富多彩
More than you would expect.
你又这样了,探长
You're doing it again, inspector.
怎么样?
What's that?
不说话,让别人说个不停
Standing mute, so that one is forced to run on and on
不想说的都说了
more than ever one would wish.
我是让你待在我的视线以内,马普尔小姐
I'm keeping you where I can see you, Miss Marple.
你都让我一半的同行自叹不如了
You may have disgrace half the men in my profession.
但是我不会这样的
But you shan't disgrace me.
我也希望不会这样,探长
I hope not, inspector.
我很羡慕你,业余侦探
I envy you, you know, the amateur sleuth.
没什么好失去的
One has nothing to lose, somehow.
不过,有薪水可拿...是很有用的
Still, a salary is er...convenient.
确实
Indeed.
要不是亏了我的侄子...   雷蒙德
If it wasn't for the generosity of my nephew...   Raymond.
我看的一些案宗里写的
So I've read in a dozen case files.
是的
Yes.
名字可不怎么高贵
Hardly a distinguished name.
你说雷蒙德?   不是
Raymond?   No.
烟囱大厦
Chimneys.
直到你站在这里,才觉得很贴切
Until it stands before one, and then it all makes sense.
有一打呢
Dozens of them.
真壮观
Splendid.
这些塔楼,很骄傲地挺立...
That great tower standing proud, so that...
凯德先生说谋杀发生的那晚是哪扇窗子亮了?
Which was the window Mr Cade
said was lit up on the night of the murder?
右数第二间?   议员的房间
Second from the right?    The MP's room.
但是,你走到凯德先生站的地方
And yet, as one approaches the spot where Mr Cade stood,
有一扇窗是看不到的,注意到了吗?
a window is obscured. Do you see?
由于塔楼的原因
On account of the tower.
所以看上去是右数第二间,实际上...
So that what appears to be second from the right is, in fact...
是第三间
Third from the right.
那么快要枪响的时候是谁起来了呢?
So who was up and about moments before the gunshot?
柴德维尔,能谈谈吗?
Miss Treadwell, might I have a word please?
11点33分的时候你的卧室灯是亮的
At 33 minutes past 11 your bedroom light was on,
距枪响只有12分钟
12 minutes before the gunshot.
是,就那么一会
Yes. Briefly.
能说说是为什么吗?
Can you tell me why?
我想跟路德维格伯爵说话
I wished to speak to Count Ludwig,
不过他床上没人,我就回屋了
but noticing his bed was unoccupied, I returned to my room.
你为什么想跟他说话呢?
Any particular reason for wishing to speak to him?
哦,他...
Oh, he'd...
他早些时候说过想加条毯子
earlier in the evening he'd asked for an extra blanket.
你生火了吗?
So perhaps you lit a fire?
什么?   还是11点33的时候
I beg your pardon?    At the same time. 11:33.
没有,昨晚没生火
No fires last night. I...
要是有人生火了我会知道的
I would have known, you see.
你知道,昨天我有种奇怪的感觉你好像认识他
You know, it's funny, but yesterday I really felt that you knew him.
看起来是个大场面啊
This looks a very grand affair.
他们那个时候是很气派的
That's how they did it in those days.
这后面的是乐队吗?
And this would be the orchestra, at the back here?
他们那天演奏的是什么?
What sort of music did they play?
华尔兹,大部分是
Waltzes, mainly.
维也纳华尔兹吗?
Viennese waltzes?
这是他,是不是?那里,路德维格伯爵
It's him, isn't it? There. Count Ludwig.
这么说他以前来过
So he has been here before.
还是在乐队里呢
And where else but in the orchestra?
这么多年后为什么又回来呢?
What brought you back after all these years?
柴德维尔小姐,你知道吗?
Any thoughts, Miss Treadwell?
他是自作孽不可活   你说什么?
He got no more than he deserved.   I'm sorry?
那个女孩...    失踪的女孩?
The girl who...   Who disappeared?
艾格尼丝   客厅女仆,是的
Agnes.   The parlour maid, yes.
艾格尼丝出什么事了?
Whatever happened to Agnes?
晚宴那晚,我...
That night after the party, I...
我看到光...
I saw a light...
我就是看到这座坟墓开了
This was the tomb I saw opened.
她的尸体,就倒在这里
Her body, it was down there.
我来帮你
Let me help you.
克莱门特,你没问题吗?
Clement, are you sure?
艾格尼丝
Agnes.
她的围裙
Her apron.
可怜的孩子
Poor child.
这么长时间,我们一直说她是个贼呢
All this time, we said she was the thief.
我想你应该告诉我们到底出了什么事
I think it's time you told us what happened.
女主人,她有一次跟我说
The mistress, she confided in me once.
玛德琳?   她说什么了?
Madeleine?    What did she tell you?
她说艾格尼丝那晚跟他在一起
She said Agnes was with him that night.
跟谁?
With whom?
一个音乐家,一个拉小提琴的
A musician. A fiddle player.
哦,伯爵吗?
Oh, the Count?
这么多年,你什么都不说
All these years. Not a word.
我想说的,先生.但是...
I wanted to, sir. But...
我觉得我要是说了,您会联络警察
I thought if I spoke out, you would contact the police,
就会变成一桩丑闻
and there would be more of a scandal.
这件事已经结束了您的职业生涯
It had already ruined your career and
如果宝石被偷都让您蒙羞,那...
if a stolen jewel could cast such a shadow, and then
那一条人命...
and then the theft of a life...
对不起
I'm so sorry.
我做了什么啊?真抱歉
Oh, what have I done? I'm so sorry.
怎么样?    她有所隐瞒
Well?   She's certainly hiding something.
该死
Damn.
哦
Oh.
我想找点...   什么?
Wondered if there was any...   What?
纸板
Cardboard.
我想找点...不好意思,你在干嘛?
Wondered if there was any... Sorry, what are you...?
你要纸板干嘛?   我在做点东西呢
What do you want cardboard for?   I'm making something.
我不知道哪有纸板,所以帮不了你
Yes, well, I can't see any, so if you wouldn't mind.
你打的什么主意,贝金索普小姐?
What are you up to, Miss Blenkinsopp?
只想在这该死的大房子里找点清净
Just looking for some privacy in this big, old nasty...house.
别动
Hands off.
抱歉,不打扰你了
Sorry. I'll leave you to it.
这很容易
Oh, it's child's play.
是用音乐写的数学题
It's um... It's musical mathematics.
你看看
Don't you see?
只要把音符和字母对上
One simply transposes the music from notes into letters.
这两个八度
So two octaves...
是A到O,这11个升音
take us from A up to O, while these 11 sharps
是直到Z
bring us all the way up to Z.
密信就解开了.啦啦啦!
Your coded letter. La! La-la!
拜托了,可别奉承我
Please, I cannot abide flattery.
谢谢你,瑞佛小姐
Thank you, Lady Revel. Thank you.
不客气   谢谢你,班铎
Very well.   Thank you, Bundle.
因为这样,我挚爱的上尉...
"For this reason, my beloved Captain...
我们不能再见面了
I can never see you again.
请答应我,你有一天会回来取回最珍贵的珠宝
Promise me you will return one day for the greatest jewel.
里士满二十,向北,三,向东
Richmond Twenty, North Three East."
死人口袋里的情书
A love letter in the dead man's pocket.
不完整,如果我们能多拿到几页,或有个日期就好了
Incomplete. If we had a couple more pages a date'd be helpful.
不过手稿是用圆珠笔写的
Yes, though the manuscript was written in ballpoint pen.
没错.那么说是这几年写的
Indeed. So, the last couple of years. Yes.
是告别信吗?
Oh. A farewell?
"挚爱的上尉",上尉?
"Beloved Captain." Captain?
路德维格伯爵的假名
An alias for Count Ludwig,
是为了让这段情事保密吧?
if this affair was to be kept quiet?
伯爵的秘密情人,是艾格尼丝吗?
The Count had a secret lover. Agnes?
大概是
Perhaps.
但这怎么解释?
But what do we make of this?
请答应我,你有一天会回来取回最珍贵的珠宝
"Promise me you will return one day for the greatest jewel."
是不是...?   路德维格伯爵回到烟囱大厦
Is it possible...?   Count Ludwig came here to Chimneys
不是为了铁矿,是为了更秘密的事情
not to discuss iron, but on a secret mission,
从信的内容来看,是为了取回被偷的迈索尔钻石
revealed within this letter, to recover the stolen Mysore Diamond
而这钻石就在这栋房子里的某个地方
located somewhere in this house.
怪不得要用密码写呢
No wonder it's in code.
所以他是为了这个想买下烟囱大厦
That's why he wanted to buy Chimneys.
“里士满二十,向北,三,向东”
"Richmond Twenty, North Three East."
线索近在眼前啊
The evidence was before our eyes.
凡代克的画?   他画的内容
The Van Dyck?   And the subject?
里士满公爵
The Duke of Richmond.
18,19,20
18, 19, 20.
就在这吗?
So?
就是这吧
So.
被折磨我探长
Don't torment me, Inspector.
你要是知道什么...    奇,奇...
If you're holding something back...   Want, want...
他的遗言
His last words.
除非...
Unless, of course...
墙,墙
Vunt, vunt...
除非他说的不是英语,而是他的母语
Unless of course he was speaking not English, but his mother tongue.
不是"奇,奇",而是"墙,墙"
Not "want, want", but "vunt, vunt".
是德语的"墙"
"Der Wand" in High German.
或者是带有奥地利口音的"墙"
Or "vunt" in the Austrian dialect.
什么意思呢?
Meaning?
墙,墙
The wall, the wall.
你觉得是...?
So, you think...?
你觉得钻石是藏在墙里什么地方吗?
You think the diamond is hidden somewhere in the wall?
嗯,很好啊
Well. Bravo.
不过,我觉得有个人能帮我们的忙
But, you know, I think I know a gentleman
who might shed a little more light on the matter.
你当晚是陪你教母来的吗?
You were accompanying your godmother?
叫...   索梅塞夫人
Lady...    Lady Somerset.
没错.我们以前都叫她罗比
That's right. We all used to call her Robbie.
一定很迷人
Must have been quite bewitching.
什么?   钻石
What?   The diamond.
哦,是的
Oh. I see.
对于我来说就是有颜色的石头罢了,探长
Well, it's all just coloured glass to me, Inspector.
你那里是什么?
What, what have you got there?
32年的调查记录
Notes from the investigation in '32.
也包括你的口供
Interviews with, among others, yourself.
"我完全不记得钻石什么时候没有的"
"I have no recollection of said diamond's disappearance.
"我当时在睡觉呢"
In fact, I was asleep."
我从清晨就起来到处忙活了,说真的,探长
I'd been charging about since dawn. Really, Inspector...
我注意到索梅塞夫人也很早就休息了
I see Lady Somerset retired early as well.
我们跟偷窃毫无关系,我向你保证
We had nothing to do with any theft, I assure you.
是这样的
The point is...
你看
See for yourself.
我那时年轻
I was a young rake.
她又很容易上道
She was easily led.
我懂了
I see.
至少也知道个大概了
Well, at least, I have an inkling.
他使用笔名写的吗
And he was writing under a nom de plume.
路德维格伯爵有个假名?   嗯   上尉
Count Ludwig had an alias?    Mm-hm.   The Captain.
奇怪
Odd.
还有个秘密情人呢,信里面都写着呢
And a secret lover, to boot. It's all in the letter.
谁是他的情人呢?
Who was she, the lover?
我们猜是艾格尼丝   可怜的艾格尼丝
We wondered. Agnes?    Poor Agnes.
不仅如此,伯爵好像跟钻石失窃还有关系
Not only that. The Count seems to have had a hand
in the theft of the famous diamond.
他把她甩了,是吗?
So he bumped her off, did he?
两个贼分赃不均?
Two thieves fighting over the spoils?
你们吃啊
Well, do start away, everyone.
她不是唯一的一个,不是吗?
Yes, and she wasn't the only one, was she?
唯一的受害者
The only victim, I mean.
比尔,那个什么...
Bill, where is the...?
就在这里,亲爱的
Right here, my dearest.
烟囱大厦,缩放版的
Chimneys. Not quite to scale, I'm afraid.
谋杀的那晚,我们都在楼下
The night of the murder. We all came downstairs.
没错吧?我们找不到伯爵了,所以就分头找
Yes? And we couldn't find the Count, so off we all went.
我们是分开的.是这样的
Separately. Now, this is the point.
我们都聚在这里
This is where we all were.
班铎,你在客房那边找
So, Bundle, you were upstairs in the guest wing.
乔治也是
George was there also.
柴德维尔在厨房
Treadwell, kitchen.
贝金索普小姐,在外面的空地上
Miss Blenkinsopp, I believe, was on the terrace.
比尔在书房
Bill study
我先去了楼上,然后下楼到了会议室
and I was upstairs then down to the council chamber.
我们离开有... 有五分钟吗,比尔?
We were all gone what...? Ah, five minutes, Bill?
没错
Absolutely.
至多一两分钟
One or two at most.
然后... 枪响!
Then... Gunshot!
我们都涌回到房子里,前门是大敞着的
Back we all flew, front door wide open.
关上那扇门!
Someone close that door!
没错吧
Agreed?
对
Yeah.
谁能说不会是我们之中的某个人跑到房子外
Who's to say one of us couldn't have run out of the house
穿过花园,活板门,进入通道,杀了伯爵
through the garden, trapdoor, into the passage, shot the Count
枪响之后再用一分钟跑回来
and then one minute to get back, after the gunshot,
看起来好像...
in time to make it look like...
好像我们一直都在这里呢?
well, to make it look like we'd been in the house all along?
前门到活板门是...
Front door to the trapdoor is...
多少步,比尔?
How many strides, Bill?
我们量过了,112步?112步
We measured it. 112? 112.
五分钟内跑个来回是有可能的
Five minutes there and back. It's possible.
你自己也这么说的,不是吗,比尔?
You said so yourself, didn't you, Bill?
是的
Sure.
但是我们为什么要...
But why would anybody here...?
伯爵想买烟囱大厦,不是吗?
The Count wanted Chimneys, didn't he?
你们都听到他说了
And you all heard him say that.
班铎,你那么反对卖房子
And, Bundle, you're so mortally opposed to losing the house.
我还没意识到自己至于这么绝望呢
I had no idea I was so pathetically grasping.
反正有人杀了他不是吗?
Well, somebody killed him, didn't they?
至于那个死去的可怜女孩...
And as for that poor dead girl...
我的小机灵鬼.你需要休整一下
My little fox. What you need is fattening up.
够了   是够了
Enough.    Quite.
你打算把这些都记下来吗,贝金索普?
You making notes, Blenkinsopp?
没有啊
No.
等你回到市政厅这一切就会传为"佳话"了
To think, what a pleasing oral history this will all make
back in your municipal headquarters.
不是的
Not at all.
大家都知道你打烟囱大厦的主意有好几年了
When everyone knows you've had your claws in Chimneys for years,
孜孜不倦地想办法,写信,通知
grubbing about with your letters and your polite notices,
管我们家的闲事,给我们债权人漏消息
rifling through our drawers, tipping off our creditors.
我妈妈当时病危在床呢
Mother was on her death bed,
你倒是心安理得
not that you lost a moment's sleep over that.
真不知道你为了那般   我来告诉你吧
God knows why.   I'll tell you why.
我发现她在书房里
I caught her in the study,
查看以前的家务记录,是不是?1932年的
going through the old housekeeping records, weren't you? 1932.
你是为了艾格尼丝,是不是?   你认识她?
This is all about Agnes, isn't it?   You knew her?
艾格尼丝帕克是个孩子
Agnes Parker was a child,
当她到你们这里的时候还是个孩子
a child when she was handed over to people like you.
她家人信任你们能对她好
Trusted to your care.
有一天她突然就没了,她的家人心都碎了
And when one morning she wasn't there, it broke her family's heart.
你们却没人在乎到底发生了什么
And not one of you had the decency to ask why.
我不舒服   你该不舒服
I feel sick.   Well, you might.
不是的,我不舒服
No, I feel sick.
爸爸?   克莱门特?
Daddy?   Clement?
哦,他该服药了
Oh, it's his ticker.
你的补药呢?你的补药?    少陪了
Where's your tonic? Your tonic!   Excuse me.
都要没了,就喝一大口吧
There's hardly any left. Just take a swig.
失陪   该死的汤
Excuse me.   Damn soup.
我们去呼吸点新鲜空气
Let's get some fresh air.
对不起,真对不起
I'm so sorry. I'm so terribly sorry.
柴德维尔小姐,这是什么样汤?
What kind of soup is this, Miss Treadwell?
蘑菇和鼠尾草,但是你没事啊
Mushroom and sage. But you are quite well.
哦,我晚上没什么胃口
Oh, I have no appetite by nightfall.
上了年纪就这样
One of the hidden costs of old age.
柴德维尔小姐,我有事想问你
Miss Treadwell, help me here.
你确定是伯爵杀了可怜的艾格尼丝吗?
Are you quite sure in your mind that the Count murdered poor Agnes?
你还看到什么了吗,请你告诉我
If there's anything else, then, please...?
已经很多年了
It's been so many years.
不能等早上再做这个吗?   不能
Can this not wait until the morning?   No.
熔丝
Fuse wire.
怎么会在这里出现呢?
Now, what's that doing there?
说的是啊
Indeed.
天啊,这是怎么回事
Dear me, what a business.
啊,没错
Ah, yes.
毛地黄的叶子
Foxglove leaves.
很容易和鼠尾草弄混
Easily muddled with sage.
肯定是被放进汤里了
Must have found their way into the soup.
毛地黄,它含有...
Foxglove, you see, contains...
洋地黄,有毒性的.我进屋了
Digitalis. Natural poison. I'll be indoors.
抱歉
Sorry.
简
Jane.
你来指责我的吗?
Here to rebuke me?
说吧
Castigate away.
不是
No.
不是的,你姐姐说的那些
No. Your sister's account of last night.
别管金妮说什么.她受了很大打击
Please don't mind Ginny. Her nerves are shot.
我记得你在找伯爵的时候是在楼上客房这边的
I noticed that you were upstairs, here in the guest wing,
during the search party,
所以我在想你把那些东西放在哪里了
and I wondered what became of them.
什么?
Of...?
那些法律文件,有关卖掉烟囱大厦的文件
The legal paperwork, drawn up last night for the sale of Chimneys,
你从洛马克斯先生那里拿走的那些
which you took from Mr Lomax's room.
哦,那个啊
Oh, that.
我是为了爸爸拿的,主要是为了他
Well, I did it for father's sake, in the main.
烟囱大厦曾经是他的一切
Chimneys meant everything to him once.
我们在这房子里曾有很美好的记忆
We used to have such housing days.
他退休以后,我们真正像一家人
After his retirement, as a family.
但是妈妈死后...
But of course with mama gone...
我能理解他的伤心,记忆啊,什么的,但是...
I understand he's upset, memories and so forth, but...
时间会治愈一切的
given time.
像我们家其他人那样,我...
And like the rest of my family, I have ah...
我并不是个很有激情的人
I have not much use of a passion
我有这么个大房子可以打理
I'm now chore such a great house.
确实打理的很好
Does make Verk ward alive.
那些文件呢
Now these papers.
老处女最后的避难所,不是吗?
Old maid's last refuge, isn't it?
对宠物过分的溺爱
An overweening love of domestic animals.
他们倒是没怎么回报我的爱
Not that they ever reciprocated.
他们总是喜欢柴德维尔
It was always Treadwell.
每只我们养过的狗狗
Every dog and pup we ever had.
她总是给他们起些个好笑的名字
She used to give them the funniest names.
你没必要留在这里,先生   啊,我没事
There's really no need to stay, sir.   Ah, I'm fine.
她心脏不好吗?   嗯,我不清楚
She had a weak heart?    Well, not that I knew.
哦,我就是想不通毛地黄毒怎么对她是致命的,对其他人就...
Oh, I wondered merely why the poison in the foxglove leaves
should prove lethal for her while the rest of us...
她确实操心很多
Well... she was a terrible worrier.
27年上海买的
Shanghai. '27.
她跟着我们到处走
She travelled about with us everywhere.
这个呢?
And this one?
哦...你知道吗,我不知道那是什么
Oh... Do you know, I have no idea.
我们的上尉写的
Our friend the Captain.
都是上尉写的?   看起来是的
All of them?    Looks like it.
也不是音符密码
And not in musical code.
这些不是
Not this one.
他写给谁的?
Who was he writing to?
康斯坦斯?
Constance?
她跟我们在一起那么多年了
She was with us for so many years.
都忘记她还有教名了
One forgot she even had a Christian name.
康斯坦斯柴德维尔
Constance Treadwell.
我就觉得她对我们有所隐瞒
I was so sure she was holding something from us.
康斯坦斯是路德维格伯爵的情人?
Constance was Count Ludwig's lover?
我最亲爱的康斯坦斯
My dearest Constance.
离公爵府的宴会只有九天了
Nine days until the party at the Palazzo Ducale.
感觉是煎熬
It feels like a prison sentence...
自从加拉加斯的那天每天都在下雨   上尉
It has rained every day since Caracas.    The Captain.
我疯了,为爱疯狂了
I am mad, bedlamism, with love.
但是"小羊羔"急的都跺脚了
But the lamb is stamping her little hooves.
我得停笔了
I must sign off now.
请你勇敢
Be of courage.
周五在烟囱大厦见,带着我全部的爱
Until Friday and Chimneys. All my love.
将再与你相见
...Our glorious reunion.
重新将你拥入怀中
I will take you in my arms.
我们再次奏响美丽的音乐
And we will make such light-fingered music."
柴德维尔?   我想她大概有所顾忌吧
Treadwell?   I suppose she had much to lose.
她的位置,她的生计
Her position, her livelihood.
当一份爱情转入地下的时候,激情很快就耗尽了
And when love is driven underground, it quickens its ardour.
我们曾有过这种状况,圣玛丽米德的风琴师和为他翻页的...
Oh, we had a case with our organist
and a young page turner at St Mary Mead.
是嘛
I see.
不该说人家的闲话
Well, one mustn't talk scandal.
时间,地点,威尼斯,加拉加斯
Places and times. Venice, Caracas.
他肯定是跟着她至少两年了
He must have trailed her for two years at least.
一直跟到烟囱大厦   到宴会那晚
All the way to Chimneys.   Back to the party.
但是柴德维尔,会偷钻石吗?
But Treadwell, a diamond thief?
也许是上尉鼓动她做的?
Well, perhaps it was the Captain who urged her to do it?
"小羊羔"是什么意思?
What is the "lamb" in these letters?
那是...   我想是...
That's...   Well, I think...
哦,不好意思.你说吧
Oh, I'm so sorry. You first.
艾格尼丝.以前天主教用来代指羊羔的
Agnes. Old papist word for lamb.
艾格尼丝代,上帝的羔羊
Agnes Dei. Lamb of God.
祭台助手   浪费青春
Altar boy.   Misspent youth.
所以我们能够推断出艾格尼丝帕克是传信的
So, safe to conclude Agnes Parker was the courier,
为康斯坦斯柴德维尔和她的"上尉"传递信件
ferrying letters between Constance Treadwell and her "Captain".
然后,32年宴会那晚
And then, on the night of the party in '32,
迈索尔钻石被盗
the theft of the Mysore Diamond...
艾格尼丝被谋杀了
Agnes is murdered.
差不多是这样,但是为什么杀信使呢
Wildly circumstantial, but the messenger,
路德维格伯爵杀了她是因为她发现偷钻石的事了吗?
murdered by Count Ludwig because she found out about the theft?
她知道的太多了,上尉就把她埋了
She knew too much, the Count buries her in the crypt, and, of course,
大家就会以为是艾格尼丝偷的钻石
everyone assumes that Agnes has stolen the diamond.
然后,多年之后,两个情人都死了
And then, years later, the two lovers dead themselves.
或者被杀了
Or murdered.
那该死的汤.这就让人不禁要问
That wretched soup. Which begs the question...
为什么同样的汤杀了一个人却只是让其他人不舒服呢
How can the same dish kill one of us
while provoking mere unpleasantness in the rest?
毛地黄是凶手加在汤里的
The foxgloves tossed into the soup by the killer
让我们觉得柴德维尔小姐的死是个意外
to convince us that Miss Treadwell's death was an accident.
但是实际上她确是中了别的毒死的
But, in fact, she was poisoned by something else.
什么毒呢?
But what?
我不知道   真可惜
I have no idea.   Pity.
想想我们中间是谁最先为艾格尼丝帕克挺身而出呢?
And who among us, I wonder,
has been quickest to defend poor Agnes Parker?
是的,我们上一所学校
Yes. I was at school with her.
他们家跟我家在一条街上
They lived on our street.
艾格尼丝的这件事...
This whole business with Agnes, well...
他们就是这么对待下人的,是不是?
It's how they treat them, isn't it?
你一直不相信是艾格尼丝在32年偷走了迈索尔钻石的,是不是?
You never believed Agnes stole the Mysore Diamond in '32, did you?
当然不信了,但是我没袭击谁
Of course not. But I didn't knock anyone off.
我对下毒的事也一点不知道
And I certainly don't know anything about any poison.
地黄...地什么...
Digi... digi...
但是你当时在这里...楼前的空地上
And yet here you are...on the terrace.
路德维格伯爵!
Count Ludwig!
就你自己,没有证人
Quite alone. No witnesses.
我们怎么想呢?
What do we think?
会不会是贝金索普小姐爬进通道
Could it be that Miss Blenkinsopp climbed into the passage,
开了枪...   啊...   然后又回到屋里呢?
fired the gunshot...   Ah   ..then back in the house?
我看是没什么可能
I don't think so.
我的气喘很重
Not with my asthma.
但是你看到什么了,是不是?
And yet, you saw something, didn't you?
是的
Yes.
我现在想想我看到的一定是凯德在花园里
I realise now it must have been Cade I saw in the garden.
他形迹可疑,不太像是保安
It did seem odd behaviour for a security guard.
我当时要是说点什么,叫人帮忙
I could have said something, cried for help.
我本可以阻止悲剧的发生的
I could have stopped it,
但我只是傻站着
but I just stood there.
你说的很对,探长
You're absolutely right, Inspector.
我想凯德先生快要没洞可钻了
I fear Mr Cade is running out of rope.
埃弗斯利先生
Mr Eversleigh.
看这个
Here we are.
"亲爱的凯德,来烟囱大厦"
"Dear Cade. Come to Chimneys.
"花园里有个活板门,11点45分整"
There's a trapdoor in the garden. 11:45 sharp."
是编出来的
Patent falsehood.
是的,看到大写的C了吗?
Yes, well. Note the capital C?
字母上有个缺口,看到了吗?
The letter has a little crack in it. Do you see?
再看这里,有一样的缺口
And again here, the same little crack.
那又如何?
So?
寄给凯德先生的便条看来是这台打字机打出来的
The note to Mr Cade appears to have been written
on this very typewriter.
而在送信的那天早上,是你在用这台打字机
Which you yourself were using
on the very morning the letter was dispatched.
哦,是这样
Oh, I see.
这是你写的,对不对?
You wrote this, didn't you?
一部分是我写的
Yes. Well, some of it, anyway.
我没写11点45整
But I don't remember anything about 11:45.
但是你让他来的?
But your purpose in writing the letter?
你在帮助凯德先生进入烟囱大厦?
To help Mr Cade gain access to Chimneys?
你跟凯德先生认识多久了?
How long have you been acquainted with Mr Cade?
几周了
Couple of weeks.
我赌牌输了不少钱
I lost rather heavily at cards.
这是我的恶习,赌牌
My pet vice, losing heavily at cards.
办公室的工作太无聊了
I get so crashingly bored in the office.
奥德维奇码头那里有个小屋子
There's a little room run in Aldwych, pontoon,
那些迷上玩牌的人会去
poker for the die-hards.
你输了多少?
How much did you lose?
97镑
97 quid.
反正,凯德来找我,说他能帮我偿清赌债
Anyway, in walked Cade. Said he could cover the debt.
我们可以互相帮忙
He said we could help each other out.
继续说
Go on.
弗吉尼亚
Virginia.
我在想你是不是该这么轻易就推掉乔治的求婚
I do wonder if you shouldn't have dismiss George's offer so lightly.
啊,安东尼,你就不能说点别的...   弗吉尼亚,求你了
Ah, Athony, like a stuck record. But you don't...   Virginia, please.
我有话要告诉你
I have sort of a confession.
我不是个好人
I'm not a good man.
不怎么好
Not really.
哦?   我的搭档,吉米欧布莱恩,事实上
Oh?   My partner Jimmy O'Brian, the fact of the matter is that,
如果我不帮他们拿到钻石,他们就要杀了他
that they were going to shoot him, if I didn't get them the diamond.
什么?   凯德先生
What?   Mr. Cade.
听我说
Listen to me,
我在脑子里想了一遍又一遍要怎么跟你说
the number of times I've played it over and over again in my mind.
我很害怕会失去你
I was so scared that I'd loose you, you see?
我真的希望事情不是这个样子的
And I wish it weren't like this, I...
我希望我们能回到过去重新开始一切
I wish we could go back to the beginning and start this dance again.
我,自行车,还有你
Me and the bicycle and you,
你是那么美丽,当我看着你的时候简直觉得疼
So beautiful that it hurts to look at you.
求你,不管你将要听到什么,请你相信我
Please, whatever you're about to hear, please, please believe me.
我确实是爱着你的
That I do love you.
这么说,有人在比勒陀利亚扣着你的朋友?
So, this gentleman from Pretoria who's holding your friend?
他们嗜赌,输了钱
He has a pet passion.
用钻石还债?
Diamonds?
是的
Yes.
迈索尔钻石?
The Mysore Diamond?
他给我六周,让我拿到钻石
He gave me six weeks to bring him the real McCoy
要不吉米就性命不保
or Jimmy's life would be forfeit.
那么是你策划了街头袭击弗吉尼亚以接近她?
So you staged the street assault to endear yourself to Virginia?
是的
Yes.
装好人接近并赢取弗吉尼亚的芳心
Posing as the good Samaritan to creep into
the affections of an innocent young woman.   George, please,
乔治,别说了
我头疼
my head is splitting.
袭击是谁做的?
And the assailant?
啊!
Agh!
对不起
Sorry.
你的真正目的是接近烟囱大厦
But your real purpose was to gain access to Chimneys,
因为钻石是在这丢的
where the diamond was first hidden.
我是个正派的人   切
I am a decent man.   Pah.
我是个做了件傻事的正派人,我别无选择
A decent man who did a stupid thing. I had no choice.
我也是
Ditto. Absolutely.
安东尼凯德,我以涉嫌杀害路德维格冯斯坦伯爵的罪名逮捕你
Anthony Cade, I am arresting you
on suspicion of the murder of Count Ludwig Von Stainach.
给我滚!
Get out!
我爱你
I love you.
你也得跟我们走
And you.
我也是吗?
Really?
谁都别说话,拜托了,让我清静一会
Nobody say anything, please. Just for a moment.
我想不管发生了什么事,这个屋子是我最喜欢的了
I think, despite everything,
that this must be my favourite room in the world.
我是个孩子的时候是不准进这个屋的
It was out of bounds as a boy,
所以我当然很想进来
so naturally it was where one longed to be.
这个甲胄
And this heraldic brute.
我曾想象他曾经历经征战,走过枪林弹雨
Oh, the battles we fought, through shot and shell.
想象军队,龙什么的
Armies, dragons, the whole works.
12岁那年的夏天
And one summer, 12 years old,
我刚刚够高能够打开他的面甲
just tall enough to open his visor,
才发现他什么都不是
my brother in arms was nothing at all.
里面只有空气而已
Just empty air.
如果你是在委婉地告诉我安东尼凯德不是白马王子
If this is you gently breaking the news
that Anthony Cade is no knight in shining armour,
那么我领会了
consider me rudely awoken.
不,不
No, no.
不是的,我是想说爱情是一场冒险
No, I'm saying that love is its own adventure.
别把任何人当做是白给的,近在眼前的人也是
Take no-one for granted, not even those closest to home.
简,帮帮我   不,不用
Jane, help me.   No, no.
我明白你的意思
I know what you're saying.
祝我好运
Wish me luck.
对不起乔治,打扰你办国家大事了
Excuse me, George. Sorry to barge in on matters of state.
我接受
I accept.
什么?   你的求婚,如果没过最后期限的话
I beg your pardon?   The offer. If it's still open.
我知道你很看重最后期限
I know how sticky you are about ultimata.
但是...凯德?
But... Cade?
那只是段白日梦罢了
Oh. That was a dream I had.
我现在清醒了
I'm awake now.
那,我很高兴听你这么说
Well, I'm delighted to hear it.
那好啊
Well.
很好啊
Well, well.
日子还长着呢,啊
The first of many.
喝一杯?香槟?得庆祝一下
A drink? Champagne. A toast!
你在干吗?
What are you doing?
放开他!
Get off him!
你别动
You stay there.
弗吉尼亚
Virginia!
为我们干杯
A toast. To us.
干杯  干杯.干杯   干杯
Cheers.   Cheers. Cheers.    Cheers.
那是什么声啊?
What on earth was that?
好像是房子里传出来的    不是,是通道里传出来的
It came from inside the house.   No, in the passageway.
先生,凯德跑了
Sir, Cade's escaped.
打开活板门
Try the trapdoor.
卡住了
It's stuck.
弗吉尼亚!
Virginia!
凯德先生,你这么做上了法庭会很不好看的
Mr Cade, all this isn't going to look very bright in court.
弗吉尼亚!我要你知道
Virginia! I want you to know.
我想给你一件东西 ―― 钻石
I want to give you something ―― the diamond.
我不在乎那东西
Not that I give a damn.
你是唯一值得我去为之而死的
You're the only prize worth dying for.
钻石就在这里
And it's got to be here somewhere.
我会找到它,交给你,你听到了吗?
And when I find it, it's yours. Do you hear?
安东尼!
Anthony!
好了!
Got it!
抓住他
It's him.
放开我
Get off me.
放开
Get off.
他连这个也做不好
He couldn't even get that right.
想证明什么呀?
What's he trying to prove?
至少证明了一件事
Well, he has proven one thing.
哦?   他的清白
Oh?   His innocence.
我能给你们演示一下吗?
May I show you?
抱歉
I'm so sorry.
你们准备好了就开始吧
Whenever you're ready.
大家都在位置上了吗?
Everybody in position?
在,在
Yes, yeah.
好了
Ready.
在
Yes.
好了警官,就等你了
Alright constable, when you're ready.
我们都站在那天晚上枪响的时候我们站的地方,是吗?
We were all standing just where we were
the moment of the fatal gunshot. Agreed?
是的   情况是一模一样的吗?
Indeed.   Everything just as it was?
不,枪响,太轻了
No. The gunshot, it was too quiet.
是的,枪响轻多了,探长
Yes, it was much quieter, Inspector.
想凯德先生刚刚砸锤子的声音
Like Mr Cade's hammering a few moments ago,
我们以为是枪响的那一声震得我的耳朵都疼了
whereas the sound we thought was the gunshot made my ears ring.
凯德先生,你记得,在花园里
Mr Cade, you remember, out in the garden,
那天晚上很暖和,你看到了什么?
what did he see on that warm night?
有人生火了
Someone had lit a fire.
还有我们在垃圾箱里发现了一段电线
And then that off-cut of flex
完全不明白它为什么会出现在那里
that had no business being in the compost.
那是一段导火线,探长
A piece of fuse, Inspector.
杀害伯爵的人,那晚在烟囱里点了些东西
The Count's killer lit something in the chimney that evening.
利用导火线,设计好15分钟后会炸响
On a slow fuse, timed to explode 15 minutes later,
让我们以为我们听到的是枪响
to deceive us all that what we heard was a gunshot
但实际上听到的是爆竹炸响
when what we, in fact, heard was a firework.
探长,记得你说过的话吗?
What was it you said, Inspector?
"不管怎么样,凯德先生都是在通道里被发现的"
"Like it or not, Anthony Cade was found in that tunnel
"身旁还有尚有余温的抢呢"
with the smoking gun."
但是如果那枪已经冷了呢?
But what if the gun was not smoking?
如果伯爵其实早就被射伤了
What if the Count was killed earlier than supposed,
在差一刻11点,男士们就寝之后
after the men retired from their business at quarter to eleven
但是在一个小时后铃响之前呢?
but before the alarm bell almost an hour later?
这么一来,凶手就可能是我们之中任何人了
Suddenly, the killer could be any one of us.
你确定吗?
Are you sure?
你记得伯爵在晚饭的时候,对里士满公爵画像表现出兴趣
You recall the Count's interest, over dinner,
in The Duke Of Richmond?
要是在我们都休息之后,悄悄把伯爵请下来
No great feat to quietly invite the Count back
after the rest of us were in bed,
请他看这个暗藏的机关,把它引到通道里,再打死他
show him the hidden bolt, tempt him inside, then shoot him,
把枪扔在他身边,我们发现的时候就像是凶手扔在那的
and toss the gun to be found later as if abandoned by the killer.
可惜伯爵没有马上死掉
Sadly for the Count, he didn't die straightaway.
这是凶手唯一的失误,如果他不是有意这么做的话
The murderer's only mistake, if mistake it was.
我的天!
Good God!
可怜的人,过了一会,当凯德先生发现他的时候他还活着呢
The poor man was still living when Mr Cade found him some time later.
继续说啊,简
Go on, Jane.
那些信件...
Those letters...
我真是很傻很天真
I've been woefully, unforgivably naive.
康斯坦斯和上尉,啊,多么浪漫啊
Constance and the Captain, ah, the romance of it.
让人看不出问题来了...
One gets swept along and yet...
我这么问吧
Let me pose a question.
一对情人,决心要隐瞒他们的罗曼史
A pair of lovers, determined to hide their secret,
他们当然要用假名通信了
might they not write under an alias?
所以路德维格伯爵自称上尉
Indeed, Count Ludwig called himself the Captain.
他是这样的,那么为什么只有伯爵用了假名呢?
So he did. But why just the Count and not Constance?
她不是和他一样害怕秘密被人发现吗?
Did she not fear exposure as much as him?
除非康斯坦斯也是个假名
Unless Constance was also an alias.
那么说信里的康斯坦斯不是柴德维尔了?
So the Constance of the letters was not Treadwell?
抱歉,班铎
Forgive me, Bundle.
我从你的剪贴簿里拿到了这个
I took this from your scrapbook.
一条狗,怎么了?
It's a dog. So what?
是妈妈养的第一条狗狗
Well, it's Mama's first mutt.
上尉,名字叫上尉
Captain. It was called Captain.
它特别喜欢柴德维尔,妈妈开他们的玩笑说...
It was so besotted with Treadwell Mama used to joke they were like...
他们是"完美的情人"
"Perfect lovers."
我们的妈妈想到的这些假名
Our mother must have thought of these aliases.
康斯坦斯和上尉,是我们的妈妈?
Constance and her Captain. Our mother?
她用"康斯坦斯"做假名
Took the alias "Constance".
你妈妈就是伯爵的秘密情人
Your mother was the Count's secret lover.
我不明白
I don't understand.
你是在说是伯爵和玛德琳偷了钻石吗?
Are you saying that the Count and Madeleine stole the diamond?
哦,那该死的钻石
Oh, that wretched diamond.
我们都太着迷于迈索尔钻石了
We're all so bewitched by the Mysore Diamond,
我们提出自己的假设却忘记了事实
we forge our theories and forget the facts.
要看清事实的真相
It is so important to see things clearly,
像是透过一面玻璃而不是棱镜
as if through a pane of glass, and not a prism.
不好意思
Excuse me.
抱歉
Sorry.
我的天
Good God.
可以给我吗?
May I?
我想伯爵是不可能杀了艾格尼丝
I'm afraid there's no way the Count murdered Agnes
然后带着钻石跑路的
and made off with the diamond.
因为钻石一直跟艾格尼丝在一起呢
Because the diamond has been with Agnes all the time.
就在坟墓里,是凶手留在那里的
In the tomb, just where the killer left it.
当我们找到可怜的艾格尼丝的遗骸的时候,记得吗?
When we found poor Agnes's bones, do you remember?
我们之中隐藏了一位演员
Your histrionics in the crypt.
是你拿走的,是不是?
You took it then, didn't you?
然后把它丢进池塘里
And dropped it in the fountain.
要不然你干嘛擦手呢?
Why else would you be drying your hands?
爸爸?
Daddy?
为什么?
Why?
32年宴会那晚
The night of the party, '32.
我弄丢了一个袖扣,你信吗
I'd lost a cufflink, if you can believe it.
我上楼去...
I went upstairs and then...
不,不.您不能往那边去,求您
No, no, no, no, you mustn't go in there, please.
求您听我的
Please, sir, listen to what I'm saying.
我不是有意杀她的
I'd not meant to kill her,
但她想要阻止我
but she tried to prevent me
不想我看到我妻子和那个小提琴手在一起
from seeing my wife and the fiddle player.
然后我的大脑清晰了起来
And then my mind cleared.
我拿走了钻石
I took the diamond.
把它留在艾格尼丝身边
Left it with Agnes.
他们自然会以为是她拿着钻石跑掉了
Naturally it was assumed that she had run off with it.
那后就是跟我妻子撒一个善意的谎言
Then all that remained was to tell my wife a white lie.
告诉她有人看到艾格尼丝
You told her Agnes had been seen.
和维也纳的小提琴手在一起
Cavorting with the Viennese fiddler
而他还继续给她写信
who, of course, went on writing to her for quite some time,
但是我把那些信收起来了
but I took care of those letters.
那些信只会让她痛苦的
They would only have caused her pain.
知道吗,现在想想,真是好笑
You know, it's funny, looking back.
她那么容易就相信了
She was so easily deceived.
这些浪漫的东西是多么易碎
These romances are so fragile.
根本就没有真正的忠诚
There's no real devotion at all.
不像我们之间的感情那样
Not such as we all had,
在一起,作为一家人,在烟囱大厦
together, as a family, here at Chimneys.
她并不快乐
She was unhappy.
她被困在这里,怪不得会憋出病来
Trapped. No wonder she got ill.
但是她死后,你找到了那些以前的信件
But after she died, you found the earlier letters,
是不是,上尉写给她的那些
didn't you, from the Captain?
这么多年,她一直好好保管着
She'd kept them safe, all these years.
是啊
Yes, indeed.
每一句
Every word.
所以当洛马克斯先生给你看路德维格伯爵说
So that when Mr Lomax showed you the letter from Count Ludwig,
想要来访烟囱大厦的信的时候
suggesting a visit to Chimneys
你立刻认出了他的笔迹
you knew the handwriting at once.
跟那些信件上的字一模一样,你知道...
A precise match for the old love letters. And you knew...
上尉就要来了
The Captain was on his way.
但是整爆竹干嘛?
But why the firework?
干嘛非得11点45?
Why 11:45?
埃弗斯利先生,你写给凯德先生的那封信,是不是没封口?
Mr Eversleigh, is it possible that the letter you wrote to Mr Cade
was in fact left unsealed?
你的客人到了,先生
Your guest has arrived, sir.
还留在桌上?
Still on the desk?
爵爷桌上的信,请您用快递寄出去
Letters for posting on his Lordship's desk.
你只需要加上时间
All that remained was to add the time.
你自己给凯德写了并寄了那封信
You wrote and posted the letter to Cade yourself.
然后又设计枪响在11点45分,就是要陷害凯德
And staged the gunshot for 11:45 to incriminate Cade.
要除掉你的敌人最好的办法是什么?
What better way to be rid of your enemies?
杀一个嫁祸另一个
Frame one for the killing of the other.
凯德不是什么好人,你自己也承认了
Cade is no good. You said as much yourself.
至于他打算把你拐到非洲去...
And as for this plan to ship you off to Africa...
别这么看着我
Now, don't look at me like that.
婚姻不能建立在谎言之上
You cannot build a marriage on lies.
不是应该建立在爱情之上吗?
Aren't you supposed to build it on love?
柴德维尔呢?
And Treadwell?
跟我们想的一样
As we thought.
不是毛地黄毒死的...而是你的补药
Poisoned not by the foxglove leaves...but by your tonic.
有效成分是洋地黄,过量摄入致死
Active ingredient: digitalis. A huge overdose.
我确实很后悔杀她
Now, I do regret that.
她是个忠诚的仆人
She was a faithful servant.
比你认为的更忠诚
More faithful than you knew.
你害怕她会把那段情事告诉探长
You were so fearful that she would tell the Inspector
about the affair. On the contrary.
恰恰相反
她却想尽办法保护她女主人的秘密
She was taking measures to protect her mistress's secret.
艾格尼丝的遗骸一被发现
As soon as Agnes's bones were recovered,
她就从你那里找到了信件放到自己屋里
she took the letters from amongst your possessions to her own room.
要是我不杀她,就不会有人知道了
If I'd let her live, no-one would have found out.
你是这个意思吗?
Is that what you mean?
好吧,那就是这样了
Well, that's it, then.
还有
Not quite.
爸爸?
Daddy?
"有一天会回来取回最珍贵的珠宝"
"Return one day for the greatest jewel."
别说了
You stop.
如果这珠宝是指的别的什么呢?
What if this jewel was a diamond of a different kind?
别说了!   不管是什么我们有权知道
Stop!   Whatever it is, we have a right to know.
玫瑰
A rose.
不是随便什么玫瑰
Not just any rose.
是里士满玫瑰
The Richmond rose.
"里士满二十,向北,三,向东"
"Richmond Twenty, North Three East."
里士满指的不是画像
The Richmond referred to is not the portrait.
没错,而是里士满玫瑰
Precisely. The rose of Richmond.
啊
Ah.
那么这些方向,是指向哪里的?
Well, these directions, where did they lead?
1,2...
One, two...
我不明白
I don't understand.
简?
Jane?
记得伯爵的遗言吗?
The Count's last words. Do you remember?
墙,墙
Der Wand. The wall.
我们以为他指的是通道里的墙
We thought he meant the wall in the passageway.
但是这美国藤,什么时候栽种的?
But this Virginia creeper, when was it planted?
玛德琳23年前栽下的,庆祝你的出生
Madeleine planted it 23 years ago to celebrate your birth.
美国藤(弗吉尼亚藤)
Virginia creeper.
我想他临死的时候一定想明白了
He knew, I'm sure he did, as he lay dying.
玫瑰,舞蹈...
The rose, the dance...
都变得明朗起来
..it all made sense.
我想那封密信是你妈妈临死的时候写给伯爵的
I think your mother wrote to the Count,
shortly before she passed away.
那封密信
The coded letter?
她不想让秘密跟她一起埋入地下
She didn't want the truth to die with her, not quite.
你的意思是...   你就是"最珍贵的珠宝"
So, you mean...   You were the "greatest jewel".
他来带你走的
He'd come to take you away.
我的小姑娘
My own little girl.
我的女儿
My darling girl.
他是我生父?
He was my father?
不,不
No. No.
如果你现在想放手...   我不会的
I feel, if you were to let go now...   I won't.
我就会离开...   我不会的
I'd just float off and...   I won't.
来吧,该来的躲不掉
Come on. No use putting off the inevitable.
你来说还是我来说?
Are you going to tell her or shall I?
我想我来说比较好
Oh, I think it's best coming from me.
贝金索普!
Blenkinsopp!
哦,天啊
Oh, dear.
哦,天啊.班铎肯定不喜欢这样
Oh, dear. Bundle won't like that at all.
但是你们不是要把烟囱大厦卖掉吧?
But you're not selling Chimneys?
班铎不想在这里呆着了,我也不想
Well, Bundle couldn't bear to stay on, and I don't want to live here,
你觉得呢?
so what do you think?
把麻烦都丢给贝金索普
Pass the whole headache on to Blenkinsopp
让她去打理吧.干嘛不呢?
and her tea and scones. Why not?
她不会有事吧,我是说班铎?
Will she be all right? Bundle, I mean.
她会把精力放在别的什么地方
Oh, she'll foist herself onto some undeserving cause.
她爸爸?   大概吧
Her father?    I suppose.
那你呢?
And you?
他们来了
Here they come.
幸福的婚姻
A happy marriage.
也不会很难吧,是不是?
It can't be that difficult, can it?
跟随自己的心愿
Go with your heart.
像妈妈那样?
Like mother?
我一直在想,她要是真那么爱伯爵
I keep thinking, if she loved her Count so much,
为什么她又那么轻易的就相信他会跑掉呢?
why was she so quick to believe he'd run off?
我想爱真的需要勇气吧
I suppose love is an act of courage.
是的
Yes.
马普尔小姐   再见了,探长
Miss Marple.   Goodbye, Inspector.
谢谢你,现在我知道我太在意自己的名声了
Thank you. I see now I've grown too fond of my own reputation.
我那么想找到那该死的钻石
I was so bewitched by the blasted diamond.
现在看看我,成了你又一个手下败将
And now look at me. The latest of your casualties.
你看怎么样?   哦
What do you think?   Oh.
国际刑警组织想让我带着它去南非
Interpol want me to take it to South Africa,
给比勒陀利亚的那个家伙下个套
entrap this villainous fellow from Pretoria.
你知道探长,我真是不在乎这个钻石
You know, Inspector, I don't care for it at all.
再见
Goodbye.